Guide to the William Sloane Coffin, Jr. Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional Material, 1918-1996; Accession 2004-M-009
  - Writings
    - Books
      - Sermons
        - Yale years: Battell Chapel [unless otherwise noted]
          - "In the End He Appeared to Me", 1961 April 2 (Box 19, Folder 321)
          - Untitled, "The finest part of any minister's life is spent, not publicly, much as he may love to preach...", 1961 December 10 (Box 19, Folder 322)
          - Untitled, "Even in this difficult stretch of history...", 1962 April 22 (Box 19, Folder 323)
          - Untitled, "To say a few words on love and marriage would seem appropriate for at least these reasons...", 1962 May 6 (Box 19, Folder 324)
          - Untitled, "In the latest issue of the Reporter Magazine, Max Frankel says that the Hallowe'en [sic] to New Years the nation moved from an eyeball-to-eyeball to a highball-to-highball confrontation...", 1963 January 6 (Box 19, Folder 325)
          - Untitled, "In dealing with any historical event we have to remember that once all the facts are in we still haven't got the truth...", [1963 December 13] (Box 19, Folder 326)
          - Untitled, "Said the Englishman to the New York cab driver: 'You can't fool all the people all the time...'", 1964 February 9 (Box 19, Folder 327)
          - Untitled, "For sheer cruelty, it would be hard to beat that last sentence; and if the parable as a whole represents good business ethics, then the Sherman Anti-Trust Law is downright un-Christian...", 1964 October 4 (Box 19, Folder 328)
          - Untitled, "Perhaps you feel as I do that Paul is sometimes a little hard to take...", 1964 November 1 (Box 19, Folder 329)
          - Untitled, "How are we to read this story? I suggest first as the story of a miracle pure and simple...", 1964 November 15 (Box 19, Folder 330)
          - Untitled, "Earlier this week, I had a cynical thought. A former naval chaplain was telling me that when sailors leave a ship to go on shore leave they have to salute twice, once towards the afterdeck, once towards the quarterdeck...", 1964 December 13 (Box 19, Folder 331)
          - Untitled, "I find Hebrews 12 a very difficult chapter...", 1965 January 10 (Box 19, Folder 332)
          - Untitled, "With the possible exception of those who think students want only to snatch scepters from imagined tyrants, and with the possible exception of those who think Yale is only fitted to train men for the steam room of the Racquet Club...", 1965 March 7 (Box 19, Folder 333)
          - Untitled, "In a highly dramatic moment in Arthur Miller's "Incident at Vichy", Dr. LeDuc, a Jewish psychiatrist, forces Prince von Berg to recognize his complicity with the forces of Nazism he despises...", 1965 April 16 (Box 19, Folder 334)
          - Untitled, "Let me first read you a rather remarkable little story, dictated by one Sam Marshall, who is a member of Miss Baird's first grade in the Dalton School in New York City...", 1965 April 18 (Box 19, Folder 335)
          - Untitled, "Twenty years ago, with the advancing allies but a few milies from the prison camp at Flossenburg, Dietrich Bonhoeffer was executed by the Nazis for his long involvement in German efforts to overthrow Hitler...", 1965 May 16 (Box 19, Folder 336)
          - Untitled, "Whenever a preacher decides he wants to preach on a passage such as this one, a passage which really shakes like an earthquake the foundation of normal human thinking...", [1966?] (Box 19, Folder 337)
          - "The Spirit of Lamech", 1966 January 9 (Box 19, Folder 338)
          - Untitled, "Obviously the barbarism of today's world cannot help but bruise the soul of anyone who is at all intellectually serious and morally acute...", 1966 April 10 (Box 19, Folder 339)
          - Untitled, "Last weekend at the annual Freshmen Conference, Mr. Webber of the East Harlem Parish suggested that one reason for the current success of the "God is Dead" movement is that middle class folk...", 1966 September 18 (Box 19, Folder 340)
          - "Some Thoughts on the Ministry", 1966 November 20 (Box 19, Folder 341)
          - "On Learned Paralytics", 1967 March 5 (Box 19, Folder 342)
          - Untitled, "This sermon, such as it is, was born in an exchange between a company Vice-president, fiftyish, very able, and a graduate student, hippy and very bearded...", 1967 May 7 (Box 19, Folder 343)
          - Untitled, "If further evidence is needed, the events of the summer certainly convinced us that things are a bit awry, if not profoundly wrong, in this country...", 1967 September 17 (Box 19, Folder 344)
          - "On Martin Luther", 1967 November 5 (Box 19, Folder 345)
          - "On Hope", 1968 January 7 (Box 19, Folder 346)
          - Untitled, "There is in the experience of parachuting at night one glorious moment...", 1968 February 4 (Box 19, Folder 347)
          - Untitled, "This is a great passage [for] inhuman and inhumanly difficult times...", [circa 1968 fall] (Box 19, Folder 348)
          - "The Whole Creation Will Be Set Free", 1968 September 22 (Box 19, Folder 349)
          - "Our Father", 1968 November [17?] (Box 19, Folder 350)
          - Untitled, "In the St. Matthew Passion, during the scene of the Last Supper Christ makes the simple shattering statement: 'One of you will betray me...'" [location unknown], 1969 (Box 19, Folder 351)
          - Untitled, "Until advent of women Jews were the best thing Yale had going for it...", [post-1969] (Box 19, Folder 352)
          - Untitled, "'And what shall I say, Father, save me..' Why not? What could be more human...", [1969 Jan/Feb?] (Box 19, Folder 353)
          - Untitled, "This barnbuilder is pretty naïve...", 1969 February 9 (Box 19, Folder 354)
          - Untitled, "Peter Stone, librettist of the musical 1776 wrote recently...", [post-1969 Mar] (Box 19, Folder 355)
          - "Service of Remembrance", 1969 June 15 (Box 19, Folder 356)
          - Untitled, "Two weeks ago I took up the suggestion of Thomas Merton and Erik Erikson and others that non-violence badly needs redefinition...", 1969 October 5 (Box 19, Folder 357)
          - Untitled, "Possibly these [conclusions?] may help us understand the impasse at the Yale Law School..." [excerpt of a sermon], [1969?] November 2 (Box 19, Folder 358)
          - Untitled, "What then shall we say to these things...", [1969 Dec] (Box 19, Folder 359)
          - "Amos and Amaziah", 1970 (Box 19, Folder 360)
          - "Sermon on Jonah", 1970 March 1 (Box 19, Folder 361)
          - Untitled, "Certainly that is a tender, beautiful, and excruciatingly difficult story...", 1970 March 29 (Box 19, Folder 362)
          - Untitled, "Over the last two and three years I have often had the pleasure of addressing Yale alumni...", [1970 October 18] (Box 19, Folder 363)
          - Untitled, "I'd be curious how all of us hear those staggering assertions which come cascading, one upon another, more evocative, I suppose than descriptive, certainly more poetic than prosaic, almost more musical than literary...", 1970 December 13 (Box 19, Folder 364)
          - Untitled, "It has been said that if a man doesn't stand for something, he will fall for anything...", [1971?] (Box 19, Folder 365)
          - Untitled, "I'm sure all of you, or many of you at least, had the same trouble I did wishing other people 'a happy New Year...'", 1971 January 10 (Box 19, Folder 366)
          - Untitled, "Even the Xmas story, read unsentimentally, is pretty bleak...", 1971 [April 9] (Box 19, Folder 367)
          - Untitled, "Now I'm just sure there is some mean spirited fellow in the congregation today who thinks I've deliberately chosen the story of a father's attempt to sacrifice his son, knowing that it's parents' weekend...", 1971 [October 24] (Box 19, Folder 368)
          - "Whom the Lord loves He chastens", 1971 November 21 (Box 19, Folder 369)
          - [Unidentified sermons], [1972-1973] (Box 19, Folder 370)
          - Untitled, "I suspect that in the New Testament there is very little generalized truth, particularly in the Gospels...", 1972 February 6 (Box 19, Folder 371)
          - Untitled, "We have sung, 'Create in me a clean heart, oh God and renew a right spirit within me,' a beautiful anthemn [sic] of Brahms...", 1972 February 20 (Box 19, Folder 372)
          - Untitled, "Good Friday says deeply personal things to each of us about our relationship to God, to each other and to ourselves...", 1972 [March 31] (Box 19, Folder 373)
          - Untitled, "I'm sure it's appropriate, and hopefully it is interesting to you because it is certainly to me, to try and say just a few words about the experiences of the last couple of weeks...", 1972 October 1 (Box 19, Folder 374)
          - Untitled, "We sang 'The Spacious Firmament on High' not to celebrate its rationalistic theology...", 1972 October 15 (Box 19, Folder 375)
          - Untitled, "Often we force ourselves to feel pity because otherwise our essential indifferences would be intolerable to us..." [series of sermons on Jesus' last words", [1973?] (Box 19, Folder 376)
          - Untitled, "There is among us these days a certain slackness of spirit...", 1973 February 11 (Box 19, Folder 377)
          - Untitled, "First three prefatory remarks...", 1973 February 18 (Box 19, Folder 378)
          - Untitled, "Thinking for a moment of Moses' overwhelming experience I suppose that we would have to say in a world that is so totally overwhelming it's hard to be overwhelmed anymore...", 1973 March 11 (Box 19, Folder 379)
          - Untitled, "When I was a boy progress was widely viewed as an escalator automatically carrying everyone and everything upwards and onwards...", 1973 April 22 (Box 19, Folder 380)
          - Untitled, "It is written that when St. Theresa put down St. Augustine's Confessions she said, "I see myself there reflected...'", 1973 April 29 (Box 19, Folder 381)
          - Untitled, [notes for a sermon], [1974-1975?] (Box 19, Folder 382)
          - "David and Saul and the United States" [Memorial Church, Stanford University], 1974 May 5 (Box 19, Folder 383)
          - Untitled, "According to one interpretation of this parable, Jesus is trying to tell his followers what will happen to those who don't serve Rome...", 1974 September 8 (Box 19, Folder 384)
          - Untitled, "On the theory that a Christian minister should not only preach the divinity of Christ, but be willing to show forth his own humanity, let me introduce the subject of our morning meditation on a personal note...", 1974 September 15 (Box 19, Folder 385)
          - Untitled, "'The scarcest human attribute in the twentieth century is perspective,' says Lester Brown, a world-renowned nutrition expert...", 1974 October 6 (Box 19, Folder 386)
          - Untitled, "I don't know how you react when you read the sentiments which always accompany the 137th psalm...", 1974 October 20 (Box 19, Folder 387)
          - Untitled, "The last statement in this morning's lesson, 'If they do not hear Moses and the prophets, they will not hear one who rises from the dead...'", 1974 November 3 (Box 19, Folder 388)
          - Untitled, "Now it's a great mistake to allegorize a parable: that is, we must not try to make a theological point out of every verse...", 1974 December 1 (Box 19, Folder 389)
          - Untitled, "...Babies always disarm us...And then unlike almost all other human beings babies don't judge us...", 1974 December 15 (Box 20, Folder 390)
          - Untitled, "For a while yesterday I thought there would be no sermon so tired was I after two intense days at a conference in New York on religion and higher education...", 1975 January 19 (Box 20, Folder 391)
          - Untitled, "'Do not be anxious about your life.' Twenty-five years ago when I was a senior at Yale Divinity School...", 1975 February 23 (Box 20, Folder 392)
          - Untitled, "Like the 'Bayonne Bleeder,' Chuck Wepner, March has held on, fighting to the last, right into the fifteenth round...", 1975 March 30 (Box 20, Folder 393)
          - Untitled, "Very comforting, the words that seem to straighten everything out for a moment anyway...", 1975 April 13 (Box 20, Folder 394)
          - Untitled, "In place of the Gospel lesson I will read part of a sermon delivered by the Reverence John Winthrop...", 1975 May 11 (Box 20, Folder 395)
          - Untitled, "In childhood we were told that George Washington once threw a silver dollar across the Rappahannock River...", 1975 September 21 (Box 20, Folder 396)
          - Untitled, "Two weeks ago I suggested that if our faith was not to lack the integrity that faith enjoins, that if with Augustine 'we believe in thinking and wish to think in believing...'", 1975 October 5 (Box 20, Folder 397)
          - Untitled, "For over a year the gaze of those of us who dwell on the campus has often been arrested by the eye-catching sign of the Career Advisory Office...", 1975 October 26 (Box 20, Folder 398)
          - "Ich habe genug of this", 1975 November 2 (Box 20, Folder 399)
          - "An Upbeat Sermon on Death" [Sage Chapel, Cornell University], 1975 November 9 (Box 20, Folder 400)
          - Untitled, "First of all let me begin by saying I am really looking forward to Thanksgiving as I hope you are...", 1975 November 23 (Box 20, Folder 401)
          - Untitled, "And to those lines we might add two more from Christopher Fry..." [farewell sermon], 1975 December 14 (Box 20, Folder 402)
          - "America Battling Headwinds and a Rough Sea" [Stanford Memorial Church], 1976 July 4 (Box 20, Folder 403)
        - Riverside years: Riverside Church [unless otherwise noted]
          - "A World Fit for Children", 1977 November 20 (Box 20, Folder 404)
          - "Born to Set Thy People Free", 1977 December 4 (Box 20, Folder 405)
          - "A Sign that is Spoken Against", 1977 December 18 (Box 20, Folder 406)
          - "Power Comes to Its Full Strength in Weakness", 1977 December 25 (Box 20, Folder 407)
          - "Moses, Moses....Here I Am", 1978 January 15 (Box 20, Folder 408)
          - "On Changing Water to Wine", 1978 February 5 (Box 20, Folder 409)
          - "Lincoln's Religion", 1978 February 12 (Box 20, Folder 410)
          - "A Gesture of Reconciliation", 1978 March 5 (Box 20, Folder 411)
          - "Our Resurrection, Too", 1978 March 26 (Box 20, Folder 412)
          - "Whether We Live or Whether We Die", 1978 April 9 (Box 20, Folder 413)
          - "Nature and Nature's God", 1978 April 30 (Box 20, Folder 414)
          - "The Ships", 1978 July 2 (Box 20, Folder 415)
          - "The Twenty-Third Psalm", 1978 July 16 (Box 20, Folder 416)
          - "Except We Be as Children....", 1978 July 23 (Box 20, Folder 417)
          - "The Wages of Grace" [location uncertain], 1978 September 24 (Box 20, Folder 418)
          - "On Winning Defeats", 1978 October 1 (Box 20, Folder 419)
          - "Triumphantly Normal", 1978 October 8 (Box 20, Folder 420)
          - "Access", 1978 October 22 (Box 20, Folder 421)
          - "And the Greatest of These", 1978 November 19 (Box 20, Folder 422)
          - "Be On the Watch", 1978 December 3 (Box 20, Folder 423)
          - "The Courage of Hope", 1978 December 10 (Box 20, Folder 424)
          - "Rejoice in the Lord Always", 1978 December 17 (Box 20, Folder 425)
          - "The Fear of Christmas", 1978 December 24 (Box 20, Folder 426)
          - "Some Thoughts on Martin's Fiftieth", 1979 January 14 (Box 20, Folder 427)
          - "The Uses and Misuses of Suffering", 1979 February 18 (Box 20, Folder 428)
          - "Ride On, Ride On, In Majesty", 1979 April 8 (Box 20, Folder 429)
          - "Living the Truth in a World of Illusions", 1979 April 15 (Box 20, Folder 430)
          - Untitled, "Before turning our thoughts toward baptism and church membership, let me make just a few prefatory remarks...", 1979 May 20 (Box 20, Folder 431)
          - Untitled, "Dear graduating seniors, faculty, your mothers and fathers (without whom, let us face it, none of us would be here) and your sisters, your cousins..." [University Chapel, Colgate University], 1979 May 27 (Box 20, Folder 432)
          - "A Message from Christians in Cuba", 1979 July 1 (Box 20, Folder 433)
          - "Neither Do I Condemn You", 1979 July 15 (Box 20, Folder 434)
          - "The Real Renewable Resources", 1979 July 22 (Box 20, Folder 435)
          - "And Jesus Looking Upon Him Loved Him", 1979 September 16 (Box 20, Folder 436)
          - "Without a Vision the People Perish", 1979 October 28 (Box 20, Folder 437)
          - "The Twenty-Third Psalm", 1979 November 11 (Box 20, Folder 438)
          - "John 3:16", 1979 November 18 (Box 20, Folder 439)
          - "Iran", 1979 December 2 (Box 20, Folder 440)
          - "Emmanuel", 1979 December 9 (Box 20, Folder 441)
          - "Sinner Cryin', Come Here, Lord", 1979 December 16 (Box 20, Folder 442)
          - "And Pray for Iranians, Too", 1979 December 23 (Box 20, Folder 443)
          - "Report from Teheran", 1979 December 30 (Box 21, Folder 444)
          - "Judge Not that You Be Not Judged", 1980 January 27 (Box 21, Folder 445)
          - "Beating the Blues", 1980 February 3 (Box 21, Folder 446)
          - Untitled, "Last week for a Lenten meditation, we sought to establish not the banality of evil, but the evil of banality..." [probably Riverside, but location uncertain], 1980 March 2 (Box 21, Folder 447)
          - "As Once They Did", 1980 March 30 (Box 21, Folder 448)
          - "Thorns in the Flesh", 1980 May 11 (Box 21, Folder 449)
          - "July 4th", 1980 July 6
            See: Accession 2004-M-009, 1918-1996 Folder 47
          - "On Humility", 1980 October 12 (Box 21, Folder 450)
          - "Continuing Reformation", 1980 October 26 (Box 21, Folder 451)
          - "Those Stirring Saints", 1980 November 2 (Box 21, Folder 452)
          - "The Everyday Saints", 1980 November 9 (Box 21, Folder 453)
          - "Thanksgiving 1980", 1980 November 27 (Box 21, Folder 454)
          - "Unto Us a Child is Born", 1980 December 14 (Box 21, Folder 455)
          - "Christmas 1980", 1980 December 21 (Box 21, Folder 456)
          - "Of Thine Own Have We Given Thee", 1981 January 18 (Box 21, Folder 457)
          - "Ordained to Unrest", 1981 February 1 (Box 21, Folder 458)
          - "Amo, Ergo Sum", 1981 February 15 (Box 21, Folder 459)
          - "Burn-Out", 1981 March 8 (Box 21, Folder 460)
          - "Alone, Yet Not Alone", 1981 March 29 (Box 21, Folder 461)
          - "Your God is Too Big", 1981 April 5 (Box 21, Folder 462)
          - "Heroes and Heroines for God", 1981 April 12 (Box 21, Folder 463)
          - "Rending the Bond of Love" [also contains correspondence from 1988], 1981 April 17 (Box 21, Folder 464)
          - "Not as a Memory", 1981 April 19 (Box 21, Folder 465)
          - "The Practice of Peace" [sermon with Jose Jorge Siman], 1981 April 26 (Box 21, Folder 466)
          - "The Road to Emmaus", 1981 May 3 (Box 21, Folder 467)
          - "Mother of Us All", 1981 May 10 (Box 21, Folder 468)
          - "The Hostility Stops Here", 1981 May 24 (Box 21, Folder 469)
          - "Competitors for the Throne", 1981 May 31 (Box 21, Folder 470)
          - "Limitations", 1981 July 5 (Box 21, Folder 471)
          - "Homosexuality", 1981 July 12 (Box 21, Folder 472)
          - "The Courage to be Well", 1981 July 19 (Box 21, Folder 473)
          - "Abortion", 1981 July 26 (Box 21, Folder 474)
          - "Being Called", 1981 September 27 (Box 22, Folder 475)
          - "The Broken Body", 1981 October 4 (Box 22, Folder 476)
          - "The Ultimate Form of Slavery", 1981 October 11 (Box 22, Folder 477)
          - "Single and Christian", 1981 October 18 (Box 22, Folder 478)
          - "The Greatest Hope", 1981 December 6 (Box 22, Folder 479)
          - "A Habit for Caring", 1981 December 13 (Box 22, Folder 480)
          - "The First Fruit of Love", 1981 December 20 (Box 22, Folder 481)
          - "Extending Christmas", 1981 December 27 (Box 22, Folder 482)
          - "What Made the Wise Men Wise?", 1982 January 10 (Box 22, Folder 483)
          - "Leaving Home", 1982 January 17 (Box 22, Folder 484)
          - "One-Talent People", 1982 January 24 (Box 22, Folder 485)
          - "The Extra in the Ordinary", 1982 February 7 (Box 22, Folder 486)
          - "There by the Grace of God Go I", 1982 February 21 (Box 22, Folder 487)
          - "Insidious Realism", 1982 February 28 (Box 22, Folder 488)
          - "We Know Not What We Do", 1982 March 7 (Box 22, Folder 489)
          - "The Grace of Dependency", 1982 March 14 (Box 22, Folder 490)
          - "The Good Friday Crowd", 1982 March 21 (Box 22, Folder 491)
          - "Our Father's Business", 1982 March 28 (Box 22, Folder 492)
          - "Palm Sunday 1982", 1982 April 4 (Box 22, Folder 493)
          - "The Human Race Fully Alive", 1982 April 11 (Box 22, Folder 494)
          - "Where the Heart Is", 1982 April 25 (Box 22, Folder 495)
          - "Mother's Day 1982", 1982 May 9 (Box 22, Folder 496)
          - "Good Names for a Church", 1982 May 16 (Box 22, Folder 497)
          - "By Fire or Fire", 1982 May 30 (Box 22, Folder 498)
          - "The Human Century", 1982 June 13 (Box 22, Folder 499)
          - "Sail On, O Ship of State", 1982 July 4 (Box 22, Folder 500)
          - "The Prospect of Death", 1982 July 11 (Box 22, Folder 501)
          - "The Habit of Heroism", 1982 July 25 (Box 22, Folder 502)
            See: Accession 2004-M-056, 1916-2003 Box 24
          - "God's First Love", 1982 September 26 (Box 22, Folder 503)
          - "The Hundredth Monkey", 1982 October 3 (Box 22, Folder 504)
          - "Rooted and Grounded in Love", 1982 October 10 (Box 23, Folder 505)
          - "Love's True Return", 1982 October 24 (Box 23, Folder 506)
          - "Who Do You Say that I Am?", 1982 November 7 (Box 23, Folder 507)
          - "Singing to the Lord", 1982 November 21 (Box 23, Folder 508)
          - "Christian Obedience", 1982 December 19 (Box 23, Folder 509)
          - "Alex's Death", 1983 January 23 (Box 23, Folder 510)
            See: Accession 2004-M-056, 1916-2003 Box 25
          - "Loving your Enemy", 1983 February 6 (Box 23, Folder 511)
          - "Eyeball to Eyeball with the Devil", 1983 February 20 (Box 23, Folder 512)
          - "Not Self-Control but Self-Surrender", 1983 February 27 (Box 23, Folder 513)
          - "Who Tells You Who You Are", 1983 March 6 (Box 23, Folder 514)
          - "Whiners or Fighters?", 1983 March 20 (Box 23, Folder 515)
          - "Being a Christian in Jerusalem", 1983 March 27 (Box 23, Folder 516)
          - "Like Him We Rise", 1983 April 3 (Box 23, Folder 517)
          - "Be Angry, But Do Not Sin!", 1983 April 24 (Box 23, Folder 518)
          - "Neither Do I Condemn You", 1983 May 1 (Box 23, Folder 519)
          - "Ahab & Naboth", 1983 July 3
            See: Accession 2004-M-009, 1918-1996 Folder 79 - 80
          - "Death is More Friend than Foe", 1983 July 17 (Box 23, Folder 520)
          - "To Set at Liberty Those Who are Oppressed", 1983 July 31 (Box 23, Folder 521)
          - "Homecoming, Homeleaving", 1983 September 25 (Box 23, Folder 522)
          - "The Kingdom", 1983 October 9 (Box 23, Folder 523)
          - "In the Midst of You, Among You, Within You", 1983 October 16 (Box 23, Folder 524)
          - "Stewardship", 1983 October 23 (Box 23, Folder 525)
          - "A Mighty Fortress", 1983 October 30 (Box 23, Folder 526)
          - "A Present-Day Reformation", 1983 November 6 (Box 23, Folder 527)
          - "God is Love", 1983 November 13 (Box 23, Folder 528)
          - "The Sabbath Belongs to Man", 1983 November 20 (Box 23, Folder 529)
          - "An Advent Hope", 1983 December 4 (Box 23, Folder 530)
          - "Christ's Plan", 1983 December 11 (Box 23, Folder 531)